RG 032, Emergency Relief Commission
Connecticut State Library
Emergency Relief Commission records
1933-1937
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Emergency Relief Commission
63.5 cubic feet
The General Assembly created the Emergency Relief commission in 1933 as a sucessor to the Connecticut State Emergency Committee on Employment and the Connecticut Unemployment Commission. It had two functions: approval of local municipal bonds for relief purposes and supervision of emergency unemployment relief projects.
RG032
T001431
Historical Note
The Commission was created by an Act of the General Assembly (1933, Public Acts, Ch. 276), effective June 7, 1933. Although its functions were somewhat broader, it was clearly the successor to the Connecticut Unemployment Commission (RG 31) and its predecessor, the Connecticut State Emergency Committee on Employment. James W. Hook, Chairman of the two earlier agencies, was appointed a member of the new Commission, and Eleanor H. Little, former Research Secretary of Unemployment Commission, became the Executive Secretary and later Relief Administrator.
The Emergency Relief Commission had two main functions: To supervise emergency municipal finance and to supervise emergency unemployment relief. The first responsibility was in effect limited to the approval of local bond issues for relief purposes, which it did for Norwalk, Danbury, Westport and Waterbury. Its unemployment relief work was much more extensive, involving preparing requests for and administering Federal grants under the Federal Emergency Relief Act (May 1933), the Civil Works Administration (November 1933), the Commodity Relief Distribution program under the Agricultural Adjustment Administration (September 1933), the Civilian Conservation Corps program (April 1933) and several other smaller programs. Accounts of the activities in some detail may be found in the two published reports listed below under "Related Records". In the later pat of 1935 the work relief projects, which had been administered first under C.W.A. and then under E.R.A., were gradually turned over to the new Works Progress Administration. The Emergency Relief Commission itself continued until it terminated by limitation of statute on February 1, 1937.
See also the.
Scope and Content
The record listed below are principally those of the Engineering Department (sometimes known as the Work Division), pertaining to work relief projects in the localities or in State Division), pertaining to work relief projects in the localities or in State Government agencies. The records were carefully prepared for preservation the Connecticut State Library as described in
Experience of the Emergency Relief Commission, pp. 71-75.
Local administrative records were apparently turned over to the town clerks (Ibid., p. 67), while substantial quantities of other materials appear to have been destroyed. Others may have been turned over to the Welfare Department (now Department of Social Services).
Related Material
RG 031, Connecticut Unemployment Commission, 1931-1933.
RG 033, Work Projects Administration for Connecticut.
Report of the Emergency Relief Commission to the Governor, January, 1933-December, 1934. Wallingford: Peiper Press, 1935. 142 pp.
Experience of the Emergency Relief Commission with relief administration in Connecticut, period of the commission created by Public Acts 1933, chapter 32A, July 1, 1933 to February 1, 1935, continued by Public Acts 1935, chapter 1, to February 1, 1937. Hartford: Emergency Relief Commission, 1937. 173 pp.
Some of the records described here, as well as related material in other Connecticut repositories, are listed in
Inventory of Federal Archives in the States. Series XIII, Civil Works Administration, No. 7, Connecticut. U.S. National Archives Project, W.P.A., 1939.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Emergency Relief Commission
Subjects:
Connecticut. Emergency Relief Commission -- Records and correspondence; Depressions -- 1929 -- Connecticut; Public service employment -- Connecticut; Unemployed -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Card files; Correspondence; Drawings; Maps; Minutes; Photographs
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1933-1937
  - 1. Administrative instructions on C.W.A. work, 1933 August-1934 August; 1 looseleaf binder (Box 1)
    Mimeographed "General Letters" to local C.W.A. boards transmitting information or instructions from the State Director of Administrator, and typed instructions to inspection engineers from the Chief Inspection Engineer.
  - 1A. Minutes of meetings, 1933 June 21-1937 January 26; 2 volumes (Box 1A)
    Typed copies, usually ribbon copies, of the minutes, signed by the Secretary. They include monthly statements of expenditures from July 1933 to date, as well as other charts, statsitics and reports prepared for hte Commission.
  - 2. Statement of auditied costs for C.W.A. work relief projects, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    Summary statement indicating name and number of project, labor cost, other cost and disposition of project if transferred to E.R.A. or otherwise, with total costs for each State Government agency and each town.
  - 3. C.W.A. work relief project files, 1933-1934
    Engineering Department (Work Division) files consisting, for each town, of three folders with: project applications and reports, with related drawings, purchase orders and correspondence; inspection reports; and correspondence with local officials.
    - Town projects
      - Andover-Chester (Box 1)
      - Clinton-Granby (Box 2)
      - Greenwich-Middletown (Box 3)
      - Milford-New Haven (Box 4)
      - Newington-Stafford (Box 5)
      - Stamford-Waterbury (Box 6)
      - Waterford-Woodstock (Box 7)
    - State Government projects (Box 7)
      Arranged alphabetically by name of agency.
    - Federal projects (Box 7)
      Arranged numerically.
      - 111-663 (Box 7)
      - 681-1058, 698 (Box 8)
  - 4. C.W.A. "special program" service and women's project materials, 1933-1934 (Box 8)
    Correspondence, rpeorts, memoranda, applications for project funds, etc. pertaining to the Transient Bureau, women's projects, service projects, nurses and teachers.
    Arranged by subject.
  - 5. Engineering Department general and administrative papers on C.W.A. work, 1933-1934 (Box 8)
    Correspondence and memoranda pertaining to general and administrative matters, airport projects, disapproved projects, accident summaries and projects recommended to Washington for continuation.
  - 6. Administrative papers, 1933-1936; 5 folders (Box 9)
    This is a fragment of what appears to be the main office files of the Emergency Relief Commission. It includes material on personnel and salary changes, Connecticut applications for Federal relief grants, town reports on expenditures for relief, and 1933 reports on investigation of towns' accounting for relief expenditures.
  - 7. Administrative instructions on E.R.A. work, 1934-1937 (Box 9)
    - General letters ERA Nos. 1-188, 1934 March-1937 January; 2 looseleaf binders (Box 9)
    - Instructions to regional engineers, 1934 April-1936 February; 2 looseleaf binders (Box 9)
    - Safety letters, 1933 December-1935 July; 1 looseleaf binder (Box 9)
    - Manual of Work Division ProcedureWashington: F.E.R.A., 1934 November. 2 vols. in 1, 57 pp., 40 pp. (Box 9)
  - 8. Report of Work Relief under the Emergency Relief Commission of Connecticut, 1935 November 15; 1 vol., 246 pp. (Box 9)
    Illustrated typescript report by the Engineering Department
  - 9. Federal Transient Bureau. Report of Activities, 1934 January-1935 (Box 9)
    Mimeographed. 11 pp., and charts and tables.
  - 10. Maps of Regional Engineers districts, 1934 April-1935 October (Box 9)
    Six marked Connecticut maps.
  - 11. Report on locally supervised A 1 and F 2 type projects, 1936 March 18 (Box 9)
    Typed report on engineering and research and planning projects that were locally supervised, with a listing of the plans, maps, etc. produced.
  - 12. Summaries of W.P.A. project applications, 1935 July-December (Box 9)
    Forms listing projects for which allocation of Federal funds was requested.
  - 13. Worksheets for report to the General Assembly, undated (Box 9)
    Manuscript notes, charts, lsits and other data on engineering aspects of E.R.A. work relief projects.
  - 14. E.R.A. work relief administrative correspondence, 1934 April-1936 September (Box 9)
    Copies of outgoing letters.
    - Statewide, 1935 October 1-1936 September 1 (Box 9)
    - Safety, 1934 April 1-1935 October 1 (Box 9)
      - Statewide (Box 10)
      - Washington reports (Box 10)
      - Frequency summaries (Box 10)
    - Bridgeport District (Box 11)
    - Hartford District (Box 11)
    - New Haven District (Box 11)
  - 15. E.R.A. work relief project files, 1933-1937
    Correspondence, reports, notes, memoranda and other materials pertaining to individual projects and to program administration on the local or State agency level.
    - Projects sponsored by State Government agencies
      - Department of Aeronautics (Box 12)
      - Civilian Conservation Corps (Box 12)
      - Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station (Box 12)
      - Department of Labor (Box 12)
      - Connecticut Institute for Blind (Box 12)
      - Connecticut Prison Associatiion (Box 12)
      - Connecticut School for Boys (Box 12)
      - Connecticut State College (Box 12)
      - Connecticut State Employment Service (Box 12)
      - State Police Department (Box 12)
      - Connecticut Reformatory (Box 12)
      - Connecticut Tercentenary Commission (Box 12)
      - Welfare Commission (Box 12)
      - Fairfield State Hospital (Box 13)
      - State Board of Fisheries and Game (Box 13)
      - Legislative Commission on Jails (Box 13)
      - Military Department (Box 13)
      - Department of Motor Vehicles (Box 13)
      - National Emergency Council (Box 13)
      - Newington Home for Crippled Children (Box 13)
      - Commissioners of Rivers, Harbors, and Bridges (Box 13)
      - Shell Fish Commission (Box 13)
      - State Board of Education (Box 13)
      - Dairy and Food Commission (Box 13)
      - Department of Agriculture (Box 13)
      - Department of Health (Box 13)
      - E.R.A. (Box 13-15)
      - Connecticut State Farm for Women (Box 15)
      - Connecticut State Library (Box 15)
      - Strate NRA Compliance Board (Box 15)
      - State Board and Forest Commission (Box 15)
      - State Planning Board (Box 15)
      - Supreme Court of Errors (Box 15)
      - State Tuberculosis Commission (Box 15)
      - United States Department of Agriculture (Box 15)
      - United States Army (Box 15)
      - Veterans' Administration Facility (Box 16)
      - State Water Commission (Box 16)
      - State Works Progress Administration (Box 16)
    - Special programs (Box 16)
      e.g. "Closing out C.W.A., statewide programs, Federal research programs, etc.
    - Local work projects
      Arranged alphabetically by town, thereunder numerically by project, with often a summary for each town.
      - Ansonia-Bozrah (Box 17)
      - Branford-Bridgeport (Box 18)
      - Bridgeport-Bridgewater (Box 19)
      - Bristol-Cromwell (Box 20)
      - Danbury-East Haddam (Box 21)
      - East Hampton-Essex (Box 22)
      - Essex-Greenwich (Box 23)
      - Hartford (Box 25)
      - Hartford-Lyme (Box 26)
      - Madison-Meriden (Box 27)
      - Meriden-Milford (Box 28)
      - Milford-New Britain (Box 29)
      - New Britain-New Haven (Box 30)
      - New Haven (Box 31)
      - Newington-Norwalk (Box 32)
      - Nrowalk-Plainfield (Box 33)
      - Plainfield-Sharon (Box 34)
      - Shelton-Stamford (Box 35)
      - Stamford-stratford (Box 36)
      - Statford-Wallingford (Box 37)
      - Wallingford-West Hartford (Box 38)
      - West Hartford-Wethersfield (Box 39)
      - Willington-Windsor Locks (Box 40)
      - Windsor Locks-Woodstock (Box 41)
    - 16. Plan file, 1933-1937 (Box 41)
      Plans and drawings submitted with project applications.
      Alphabetical by town and thereunder numerical by plan number. Statewide and Federal projects filed at the end. Item 19 below is a guide to plan numbers.
      - Ansonia-Bridgeport (Box 41)
      - Bridgeport-Greenwich (Box 42)
      - Griswold-Middletown (Box 43)
      - Middletown-New Haven (Box 44)
      - New Haven-Norwalk (Box 45)
      - Norwich-Thompson (Box 46)
      - Torrington-Waterbury (Box 47)
      - Waterbury-Woodbridge (Box 48)
      - Statewide projects (Box 48)
      - Federal projects (Box 48)
      - Maps (Box 49)
  - 17. Photograph file, 1933-1937
    Photos of work relief projects in progress and complete.
    Alphabetical by town and thereunder by project number. Statewide and CWA project photos are at the end, as are pictures of works of the Connecticut Art Project.
    - Town projects
      - Index Ansonia to Windsor Locks (Box 49)
      - Ansonia (Box 49)
      - Beacon Falls (Box 49)
      - Bloomfield (Box 49)
      - Bridgeport (Box 49)
      - Bristol (Box 49)
      - Canaan (Box 49)
      - Clinton (Box 49)
      - Canton (Box 49)
      - Danbury (Box 49)
      - Derby (Box 49)
      - East Hampton (Box 49)
      - East Hartford (Box 49)
      - Enfield (Box 49)
      - Essex (Box 49)
      - Fairfield (Box 49)
      - Glastonbury (Box 49)
      - Greenwich (Box 49)
      - Griswold (Box 49)
      - Groton (Box 49)
      - Hartford (Box 50)
      - Manchester (Box 50)
      - Mansfield (Box 50)
      - Middletown (Box 50)
      - Montville (Box 50)
      - Naugatuck (Box 50)
      - New Britain (Box 50)
      - Neew Haven (Box 50)
      - New London (Box 50)
      - New Milford (Box 50)
      - Norwich (Box 50)
      - Plainville (Box 50)
      - Plymouth (Box 50)
      - Putnam (Box 50)
      - Ridgefield (Box 50)
      - Salisbury (Box 50)
      - Saybrook (Box 50)
      - Seymour (Box 50)
      - Shelton (Box 50)
      - Simsbury (Box 50)
      - Southington (Box 50)
      - South Windsor (Box 50)
      - Sprague (Box 50)
      - Stafford (Box 50)
      - Stamford (Box 50)
      - Stonington (Box 50)
      - Stratford (Box 50)
      - Thomaston (Box 50)
      - Thompson (Box 50)
      - Torrington (Box 50)
      - Trumbull (Box 50)
      - Vernon (Box 50)
      - Waterbury (Box 50)
      - Watertown (Box 50)
      - Westbrook (Box 50)
      - West Hartford (Box 50)
      - West Haven (Box 50)
      - Westport (Box 50)
      - Wethersfield (Box 51)
      - Winchester (Box 51)
      - Windham (Box 51)
      - Windsor (Box 51)
      - Windsor Locks (Box 51)
    - Statewide projects (Box 51)
      - Aeronautic (Box 51)
      - Connecticut Agrucltural Experiment Station (Box 51)
      - Department of Public Welfare (Box 51)
      - Fairfield State Hospital (Box 51)
      - Fish & Game Commission (Box 51)
      - Rivers, Harbors, Bridge Commission (Box 51)
      - State Park & Forest Commission (Box 51)
      - State Planning Board (Box 51)
      - Unidentified Prints & Negatives (Box 51)
    - CWA projects (Box 51)
      - Bridgeport (Box 51)
      - Fairfield (Box 51)
      - Farmington (Box 51)
      - Manchester (Box 51)
      - Naugatuck (Box 51)
      - New Britain (Box 51)
      - New Canaan (Box 51)
      - New Haven (Box 51)
      - New London (Box 51)
      - Norwalk (Box 51)
      - Stratford (Box 51)
      - Trumbull (Box 51)
      - Watertown (Box 51)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 51)
      - Unidentified (Box 51)
    - Connecticut Art Project
      - New Haven (Box 51A)
      - Norwalk (Box 51A)
      - Stamford & Darien (Box 51A)
      - Westport (Box 51A)
    - Oversize
      - State Parks & Forest Commission (Box 51B)
        S-Be-23, Rocky Neck State Park
      - CWA Project: Adder Brook Reservoir (Box 51B)
        Project number & town unknown
  - 18. Report file, 1933-1937
    Reports resulting from survey and research studies. These are listed in
    Experience of the Emergency Relief Commission, p. 73
    , where they are described as "Statistical Reports" (the list is not entirely accurate).
    - Bridgeport-Hartford (Box 52)
    - Hartford (Personal Pension Survey) (Box 53)
    - Hartford (Traffic)-Meriden (Box 54)
    - Meriden-New Britain (Box 55)
    - New Britain-West Hartford (Box 56)
    - State Government projects (Box 57-58)
    - Federal Transient Bureau (Box 58)
    - Student Aid Program (Box 58)
    - Loose papers, FERA and CWA, 1934-1936, undated (Box 58B)
  - 19. "Card Index Control", 1933-1937
    Card file (5 x 8 in.) containing summary data for each project, with number and description, estimates of costs, and references to final report and to plan file.
    Arranged alphabetically by town, thereunder by project number.
    - Ansonia-Greenwich (Box 59)
    - Griswold-New Hartford (Box 60)
    - New Haven-Stamford (Box 61)
    - Stonington-Woodbridge (Box 62)
    - State Government projects (Box 63)
    - Student aid projects (Box 63)
    - C.W.A. projects (Box 63)
  - 20. Federal Transient Bureau files, 1934 January-1935 October (Box 64-65)
    Correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, purchase orders, and other materials dealing with the administration of the Transient Bureau and its shelters. These are evidently papers collected from the various district offices and camps or shelters.
    Grouped roughly by office of origin and filed more or less by subject.
  - 21. Connecticut Guide files, 1933-1935
    This guide originated as a CWA project under the State Planning Board and was completed with FERA funds. A field "survey of places of scenic and historic interrest" was conducted and the collected material, compliled by Edgar L. Heermance, was published as
    The Connecticut Guide, What to See and Where to Find It. (Hartford: Emergency Relief Commission, 1935 ). 320pp.
    These papers were also used by the WPA Writers Project as reference materials for its own
    Connecticut Guide
    .
    Form survey reports, maps, photos, notes, memoranda and correspondence.
    - "How to use this file" (Box 66)
    - Subject files (Box 66)
    - Town files (Box 66)
      - A-F (Box 66)
      - G-N (Box 67)
      - O-W (Box 68)